Guide to the American Bar Association War Powers Study Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
American Bar Association War Powers Study Papers
1970-1984.
American Bar Association.
23 linear ft. (ca.17,500 items in 55 boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079318
History
In 1971 the American Bar Association formed a committee to prepare a study "...on the respective powers under the Constitution of the President and of the Congress to enter into and conduct war." The committee was chaired by Lyman M. Tondel, Jr. and the project was funded by the Association's Fund for Public Education which in turn contracted with Columbia University to carry out the study. The staff included Abraham D. Sofaer, Project Director and Adjunct Professor of Law at Columbia since 1969; Professor Milton Henry, Project Historian; Enid Sterling, Research Associate; and Columbia University Law School students who did background research and writing for the project.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, memoranda, manuscripts, typescripts, manuscript notes, proofs, photocopies of original letters, manuscripts, documents, and other supporting materials used in the research, writing and publication of the American Bar Association's "War Powers Study." The correspondence and memoranda include applications for research positions with the project and communications among the project staff. By far the majority of the papers consist of heavily corrected manuscripts and typescript drafts of each chapter for the multi-volume series entitled: WAR, FOREIGN AFFAIRS AND CONSTITUTIONAL POWERS (Cambridge, Mass., Ballinger, 1976- ). Each chapter's drafts are followed by extensive working papers which include research papers written by the staff, photocopies and transcripts of original letters, manuscripts and documents, inventories and calendars of historical documents, and excerpts from printed sources.
Arrangement
Correspondence and Financial Records, 1970-1977, Box 1a; Correspondence re. Application for Research Positions (PRTS) & Volume 1. Chapter 1 Drafts, Box 1b; Volume 1. Chapters 1-5, Boxes 2-11; Volume 1. Miscellaneous Working Papers, Boxes 12-14; Volume II. Working Papers: Executive History Incident Memoranda, Boxes 15-18; Volume II. Working Papers: Summary of Congress, Box 19-24; Volume II. Preface, etc. and Chapters 1-4, Boxes 25-32; Volume II. Revised Master Proof, etc., Box 33; Volume II. Miscellaneous Working Papers, Boxes 34 & 35; Volume II. Working Papers: Presidnetial Administrations, Boxes 36-46; Volume II. Working Papers: Events, Boxes 47-51; Post Volume II. Working Papers: Events, Boxes 52-54.
Subjects
United States.--Congress.; Columbia University.--School of Law.; American Bar Association.--Fund for Public Education.; Tondel, Lyman M.,--Jr.; Sofaer, Abraham D.; Henry, Milton.; Sterling, Enid.; Gift of the American Bar Association, 1981-1990.; Presidents--United States.; Law--Research--United States.; War and emergency powers--United States.; Constitutional law--United States.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1981 M81-11 American Bar Association Gift
- Series I: Administrative Records
  - Correspondence and Financial Records, 1970-1977 (Box 1a)
  - Correspondence re Application for Research Positions PRTS (Box 1b)
- Series II: Volume I
  - Chapter 1
    - Drafts (Box 1b)
    - Working Papers (Box 2)
  - Chapter 2
    - Drafts (Box 2)
    - Working Papers (Box 2)
  - Chapter 3
    - Drafts (Box 3)
    - Working Papers (Box 3)
  - Chapter 4
    - Drafts (Box 3-5)
    - Working Papers (Box 6-7)
  - Chapter 5
    - Drafts (Box 7-10)
    - Working Papers (Box 10-11)
  - Miscellaneous Working Papers
    - Annals of Congress (i.e., Debates and Proceedings in the Congress of the United States…1789-1824
      - Photocopies, excerpts, notes, etc.
        - vol. 1-23 (Box 12)
        - vol. 24-30 (Box 13)
      - Complete Summaries (1) (Box 13-14)
    - Master Proof (Box 14)
    - War, Foreign Affairs and Constitutional Powers: The Origins Vol. I. (Box 14)
- Series III: Volume II
  - Working Papers: Executive History Incident Memoranda
    - 1820-1853 (Box 15)
    - 1854-1890 (Box 16)
    - 1891-1904 (Box 17)
    - 1906-1955 (Box 18)
  - Working Papers: Summaries of Congress (Manuscripts, typescripts, photocopies, excerpts, notes, etc.)
    - 1841-1853 (27th-33rd Congress) (Box 19)
    - 1853-1866 (34th-39th Congress) (Box 20)
    - 1867-1976 (40th-44th Congress) (Box 21)
    - 1877-1880 (45th-47th 1st Session Congress) (Box 22)
    - 1881-1892 (47th Special Session-52nd Congress) (Box 23)
    - 1893-1899 (53rd-55th Congress) (Box 24)
  - Preface (Box 25)
  - Acknowledgements (Box 25)
  - Table of Contents (Box 25)
  - Introduction (Box 25)
  - Notes (Box 25)
  - Chapter 1--Drafts (Box 25)
  - Chapter 2--Drafts (Box 26-28)
  - Chapter 3--Drafts (Box 28-30)
  - Chapter 4--Drafts (Box 30-32)
  - Revised Master Proof (Box 33)
  - Index Proof (Box 33)
  - Index Cards (Box 33)
  - Miscellaneous Working Papers (Box 34-35)
  - Working Papers Presidential Administrations
    - 1829-1845 Andrew Jackson, Martin Van Buren, John Tyler (Box 36)
    - 1845-1853 James K. Polk, Zachary Taylor, Millard Fillmore (Box 37)
    - 1853-1861 Franklin Pierce, James Buchanan (Box 38)
    - 1861-1865 Abraham Lincoln (Box 39)
    - 1865-1869 Andrew Johnson (Box 40)
    - 1869-1877 Ulysses S. Grant (Box 41)
    - 1877-1881 Rutherford B. Hayes (46th Congress, 1st session) (Box 42)
    - 1877-1889 Rutherford B. Hayes, James A. Garfield, Chester A. Arthur, Grover Cleveland (49th Congress ) (Box 43)
    - 1881-1889 Grover Cleveland; Diplomacy during Garfield, Arthur, Cleveland (Box 44)
    - 1889-1897 Benjamin Harrison, Grover Cleveland (Box 45)
    - 1897-1901 William McKinley (Box 46)
  - Working Papers: Events
    - 1831-1837 (Box 47)
    - 1839-1847 (Box 48)
    - 1851-1871 (Box 49)
    - 1871-1895 (Box 50)
    - 1898-1902 (Box 51)
    - Cases Studies
      - Mexico, 1822-1876 (Box 51)
      - Guatemala, 1839-1900 (Box 51)
      - Panama, 1856-1903 (Box 51)
- Series IV: Post Volume II
  - Working Papers: Events
    - 1902-1917 (Box 52)
    - 1918-1950 (Box 53)
    - 1955-1972 (Box 54)
    - Congressional Hearings/Papers on Vietnam and Tonkin (Box 54)
    - Resolution (Box 54)